Guide to the Records of the King Juan Carlos I of Spain Center RG.37.33
New York University Archives
Records of the King Juan Carlos I of Spain Center
1975-2023
New York University Archives
New York University. King Juan Carlos I of Spain Center
Centelles, Agustí, 1909-1985
Mendelson, Jordana
RG.37.33
10.75 Linear Feet in 19 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 1 record carton, and 1 folder in shared housing
49.14 Gigabytes
The King Juan Carlos I of Spain Center promotes research and teaching on Spain and the Spanish-speaking world at New York University. The Records of the King Juan Carlos I of Spain Center (dated 1975-2023) consist of materials created and collected by the Center documenting its administrative activities and event programming, including correspondence, memoranda, reports, planning files, photographs, and ephemera. The records were created by administrators, directors, and fellows associated with the Center, and document the Center's administration, events, courses, and publications.
Conditions Governing Access
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred in June 2019. The accession number associated with this gift is 2019.076. In October and December 2023, Jordana Mendelson, Director of KJCC, transferred two accretions to this collection; the accession numbers associated with this gift are 2024.004 and 2024.005.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received.
Historical Note
In the early 1980s, New York University intensified its commitment to international education, community service and the global exchange of information. The University began creating centers dedicated to teaching and research on countries, cultures, and concerns abroad.
During this time, NYU's 13th president, John Brademas observed a lack of information on, and awareness of Spain and Latin America in the media, academia, and countless other institutions. In 1983, Brademas began a campaign centered on increasing awareness of Spain and the Spanish-speaking world at NYU. His first step was to honor King Juan Carlos I of Spain for his leadership and defense of democratic principles by awarding him an honorary Doctor of Laws degree. He then established a professorship in the King's name that went on to attract many of the world's most eminent Hispanists. During this time, he also announced his intention to create a center dedicated to the interdisciplinary study of modern Spain and the Spanish-speaking world.
In April 1997, in the presence of distinguished figures from Spain, Latin America, and the U.S., including the King and Queen of Spain and First Lady Hillary Rodham Clinton, the King Juan Carlos I of Spain Center was inaugurated. It promised to be the most comprehensive university-based resource of its sort. Housed in Judson Hall, the Washington Square Park landmark building designed by Stanford White, the Center solidified NYU's commitment to the study of Spain and Latin America. Unexpectedly, it also quickly became a major cultural resource for the city of New York, educating many in the community who might not be exposed to the cultures and history of Spain and Latin America.
Scope and Contents
The Records of the King Juan Carlos I of Spain Center (dated 1975-2023) consist of materials created and collected by the Center documenting its administrative activities and event programming, including correspondence, memoranda, reports, planning files, photographs, and ephemera. The records were created by administrators, directors, and fellows associated with the Center, and document the Center's administration, events, courses, and publications.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact New York University Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Exhibition catalogs.; Photojournalism.; Spanish literature; Spain -- History; Spanish language; Mendelson, Jordana
- Exhibition Catalog -- Centelles in_edit_¡oh!, 2011 (Box Shared University Archives 055, Folder 1)
- Event Photographs, 2006, undated (Box 1)
- Event Photographs, undated (Box 2)
- Event Photographs; Event Files; Guest Book, 1975-2020 (Box 3)
- Ephemera; Event Files; Event Photographs, 1997-2015 (Box 4)
- Event Photographs, 1996-2004 (Box 5)
- Photograph (Box Shared University Archives Accessions 002, Folder 5)
- Medals, undated (Box 6)
- Conferences; Lectures, 1996-2004 (Box 5)
- Conferences; Lectures; Events, 1997-2007 (Box 8)
- Conferences; Lectures; Events, 1998-2002 (Box 9)
- Conferences; Lectures; Events, 2002-2005 (Box 10)
- Conferences; Lectures; Events, 2005-2006 (Box 11)
- Conferences; Lectures; Events, 1997-1998 (Box 7)
- Conferences; Lectures; Events, 2007-2008 (Box 12)
- Conferences; Lectures; Events, 2008-2009 (Box 13)
- Conferences; Lectures; Events, 2010-2012 (Box 14)
- Conferences; Lectures; Events, 2013-2022 (Box 15)
- Conferences; Lectures; Events, 1998-2022 (Box 16)
- Conferences; Lectures; Events, 2004-2017 (Box 17)
- Conferences; Lectures; Events; Photographs; Reports, 1998-2023 (Box 18)